<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>From the shepherd of Israel, to the Bishops in England with some queries and councell to all courtiers, and judges, &amp;c, that they incense not King Charles against the Lords heritage : also, the breathings of the seed, and crie of his own elect, that his people may be preserved, which he cannot but hear, because of the incercession of his spirit, poured out upon his off-spring : this I believe, therefore I speak : also, the arise of the beast, false prophet, and anti-christ, and who they are, and what their work is, declared : and the everlasting gospell preached again to all nations, kindreds and people, and the beast and false prophet, which deceived them taken and destroyed, the accuser of the brethren cast out, and judged / given forth by Humphry Woolrich.</title>
            <author>Wollrich, Humphry, 1633?-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66857</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3292</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15081</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12596548</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12596548</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64060</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66857)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64060)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 971:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>From the shepherd of Israel, to the Bishops in England with some queries and councell to all courtiers, and judges, &amp;c, that they incense not King Charles against the Lords heritage : also, the breathings of the seed, and crie of his own elect, that his people may be preserved, which he cannot but hear, because of the incercession of his spirit, poured out upon his off-spring : this I believe, therefore I speak : also, the arise of the beast, false prophet, and anti-christ, and who they are, and what their work is, declared : and the everlasting gospell preached again to all nations, kindreds and people, and the beast and false prophet, which deceived them taken and destroyed, the accuser of the brethren cast out, and judged / given forth by Humphry Woolrich.</title>
                  <author>Wollrich, Humphry, 1633?-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1661]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64060:1"/>
            <p>FROM THE Shepherd of Iſrael, TO THE BISHOPS In <hi>ENGLAND;</hi> With ſome Queries and Councell to all Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, and Judges, &amp;c. That they Incenſe not <hi>KING CHARLES</hi> againſt the Lords Heritage.</p>
            <p>Alſo, the Breathings of the Seed, and Crie of his own Elect, that his People may be preſerved, which he cannot but hear, becauſe of the Incerceſſion of his Spirit, poured out upon his Off-ſpring. This I Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, therefore I ſpeak.</p>
            <p>Alſo, the ariſe of the Beaſt, Falſe Prophet, and Anti-chriſt; and Who they are, and What their works is, declared.</p>
            <p>And the Everlaſting Goſpell Preached again to all Nations, Kindreds and People; and the Beaſt and Falſe Prophet, which deceived them, taken and deſtroyed; the Accuſer of the Brethren caſt out, and Judged.</p>
            <p>given forth by <hi>Humphry Woolrich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London.</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon</hi> in <hi>Martins Le Grand</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:64060:2"/>
            <p>A <hi>Biſhop then muſt be Blameleſs, the Husband of one Wife, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant, Sober, of good Behaviour, given to Hoſpitallity, apt to Teach; not given to Wine; no Striker, nor greedy of Filthy Luker, but Patient, not a Brawler, nor Coveteous; one that Ruleth well his own Houſe, having his Children in Subjection with all Gravity:</hi> 1 Tim. 3.2, 3, 4.5. <hi>For if a man know not how to Rule his own houſe, How ſhall he take care of the Church of God?</hi> (na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally) as <hi>Timothy,</hi> that Biſhop did. <hi>Phillip.</hi> 3.20. where <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I have no man like minded, who will naturally care for your State; for all ſeek their one and not the things that are Jeſus Chriſts:</hi> But ſaith <hi>Paul, Ye know the proof of him, that as a Son with a Father he hath ſerved with me in the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Read ye that have taken the Names of Biſhops, or Miniſters of Chriſt, great is your work, which is to watch for the ſotil, as they that muſt give an account for it; <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.17. I ſay, Read 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. ver. 3. how <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> ſerved in the Goſpel. <hi>Giving no offence in any thing, that the Miniſtry be not blamed, but in all things, approving our ſelves as the Miniſters of God, in much Patience, in Afflictions, in Neceſſities, in Distreſſes, in Stripes, in Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in Tumults, in Labours, in Watchings, in Fastings; by Pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by Knowledge, by long Suffering, by Kindneſs, by the Holy-Ghoſt:</hi> (Mark) <hi>by the Holy Ghoſt, by love <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfained, by the Word of Truth,</hi> (the Faithful Word which <hi>Timothy</hi> held) <hi>by the Power of God, by the Armour of Righteouſneſs, on the Right Hand, and on the Left; by Honour, and Dishonour, by Evil Report and Good Report, as De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers and yet True:</hi> ver. 8, 9. <hi>As <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown, yet well Known: as Dying, yet behold we Live: as Chaſtened, and not Killed: as Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful, yet alway Rejoycing; as Poor, yet making many Rich: as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Nothing, yet Poſſeſſing all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let theſe things be conſidered by you Biſhops, Doctors or Teachers whatſoever; in Gods Love I mind you of your Duty, and Work, which is not to live at Eaſe, Worldly Honour, and Pleaſures; but to perfect the Saints, as <hi>Paul, Timothy,</hi> &amp; <hi>Titus</hi> did, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 10, 14. Neither as Lords over Gods Heritage, or Maſters over their Faith and Conſciences, but as good Stewards of the Myſteries of God, who is the cheif Shepherd of the Sheep,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64060:2"/>unto whom ye muſt all give an account, how you have uſed your Talent: <hi>Bleſſed is that Servant, when his Lord commeth, ſhall find him giving them meat in due ſeaſon,</hi> Mat. 24.26.25, 26. And 1 Tim. 3.6. <hi>A Biſhop muſt not be a Novice, least being lifted up with pride, he fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Condemnation of the Devil.</hi> Verſe 7. <hi>Moreover, he muſt have a good Report of them which are without, leſt he fall into Reproach and the Snare of the Devil.</hi> Chap. 4.1. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Spirit ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth expreſly, that in the last dayes, ſome ſhould depart from the Faith, giving heed to Seducing Spirits, and Dostrines of Devills: Forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Marry, and commanding to abſtain from Meats, which God hath Created to be Received with Thanksgiving of them that do believe, and know the Truth; for every creature of God is good, and nothing to be Refuſed, if it be received with Thanksgiving for it is Sanctified by the Word of God and Prayer.</hi> (Mark) <hi>Timothy</hi> was not to forbid the eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of meats upon any pretence whatſoever, it being lawful for them, that did believe, and knew the Truth; he might not ſay, the Law of the Land forbids it, and therefore it is unlawful: but verſe 6. He was to put the brethren in mind, that this was a Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of Devills; and ſuch as did forbid theſe things, were depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Faith, and knew not the Truth, but were unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and ſuch as had taken heed to ſeducing Spirits: (Mark) <hi>If thou put the Brethren in mind of theſe things, then ſhalt thou be a good Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, nouriſhed up in the words of Faith, and good Doctrine.</hi> Titus 1.7. <hi>For a Biſhop muſt be blameleſs, as the Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard of God, not Self-willed, nor ſoon Angry, not given to Wine, no Striker, nor given to Filthy Luker, but a lover of Hoſpitallity, a lover of good Men, Sober, Juſt, Holy, and Temperate, holding faſt the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Word, that he may be able, by ſound Doctrine.</hi> (Mark) not by Priſons, Whipping, and Perſecuting, he doth not ſay, <hi>But by Sound Doctrine, both to Exhort and Convince the Gain-ſayer.</hi> Ver. 6. <hi>He muſt alſo be blameleſs, the Husband of one Wife, having faithful Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, not accuſed of Riot, or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nruly.</hi> Read alſo, Tim. 2.2. The ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice <hi>Paul</hi> gave to that Biſhop, ver. 1. <hi>Thou therefore my Son, be ſtrong in the Grace, that is in Chriſt Jeſus, and the things thou haſt heard of me, amongſt many witneſſes; the ſame commit thou to faithful men, who ſhall be able to teach others alſo; thou therefore indure hardſhip, as a good Souldier of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> (Mark) <hi>No man that Warreth, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangleth himſelf with the things of this life, that he may pleaſe him, that choſe him to be a Souldier,</hi> ver. 8.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:64060:3"/>
He bids <hi>Timothy</hi> remember Chriſt Jeſus: ſo ſay I to all you Biſhops, and Teachers, Take Chriſt Jeſus for your pattorn, and his Light in you; and take heed how you have any hand <hi>privately</hi> or <hi>openly,</hi> in Perſecuting any for Conſcience ſake; but remember <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> the cheif Biſhop and Shepherd of the Everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, how he Perſecuted none, no not his Enemies; but he that was Juſt, and did no ſin, ſuffered by the unjuſt and ſinners, and Prayed for his Perſecuters, that knew not what they did: O let Chriſt be your Example, rather than the High Prieſts, and thoſe learned men that put Chriſt to death: Would you purchaſe to your ſelves a good degree of Honour and Boldneſs in the day of the Lord, then uſe the Offices ye are in well, and not againſt Chriſt, or the Flock he taketh care of; but let the ſame minde be in you that was in <hi>Paul,</hi> and in <hi>Timothy,</hi> where <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 Tim. 2.24, 25, 26. <hi>The Servant of the Lord muſt not strive; but be gentle unto all men, apt to Teach, patient<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in Meekneſſe Instructing them that do appoſe themſelves, if God peradventure will give them Repentance, to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging of the Truth, and that they may Recover themſelves out of the Snare of the Devil, who were taken Captiveby him at his will.</hi> Ver. 10. Therefore, ſaith <hi>Paul, I endure all things for the Elects ſake, that they may obtain the Salvation that is in Chriſt Jeſus, with Eternal Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now ye <hi>Biſhops, Doctors,</hi> and <hi>Teachers,</hi> and all ſuch that han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle the Law; Do ye all ſtand ſtill awhile, weigh your ſelves in the true Ballance, meaſure your ſelves with the Meaſure of the Spirit, that God hath freely given to every one of you, that by it ye may be ſaved from Sin, and led into all Truth: I ſay, all confider; is this the Crown ye aim at, the Salvation of the Immortal Souls? O that there were ſuch a heart in you that was in Chriſt Jeſus that Biſhop, or the ſame mind in you, that was in <hi>Paul, Titus</hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi> that laboured, &amp; watched day and night that they might preſent every man <hi>perfect in Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> for whoſe ſake, ſaith Paul, <hi>I ſuffered the loſs of all things, and do count them but dung, that I may win Chriſt, and be found in him: yea thoſe things which were gain, I counted loſs for the excellency of the knowledge that is in Chriſt Jeſus my Lord,</hi> Phil. 3.8. Saith he, <hi>That I may be found in him,</hi> (marke, in him whoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Power and Glory is not of this world,) <hi>Not having my own Righteouſnes, that is of the Law, but that which is through the Faith of Chriſt.</hi> Ver. 10. <hi>That I may know him, and the Power of his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and the fellowſhip of his Sufferings:</hi> (Mark, him that was a man
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64060:3"/>of ſorrow, and acquainted with grief, and had not a place to lay his head in; Read Iſa. 53.3. Luke 9.58.) <hi>being made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to his death:</hi> but <hi>Paul</hi> with weeping complaineth of ſome, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. ver. 18. that were of another mind, <hi>Whoſe God was their bellies, who minded earthly things,</hi> and did glory in that which might have been looked on by them as their ſhame, <hi>(whoſe end was destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,)</hi> but ſaith he, ver. 20. <hi>Our Converſation is in Heaven, from whence we look for the Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Friends! Do nothing without conſideration; and a little conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this great matter. Is this the end ye take theſe Offices of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops upon you, that ye may watch for the ſouls of the poor ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered Sheep, and ſave the afflicted and diſpiſed Lambs of Chriſt by them that are at eaſe? O this is a great work, if ye leave it not undone: Or is this <hi>the Prize</hi> ye run for, and the <hi>Mark</hi> ye aim at? then would the Lord <hi>ſtabliſh you,</hi> and the moſt Higheſt himſelf <hi>will be your Shepherd,</hi> and <hi>a Shelter,</hi> and <hi>hiding place</hi> unto you; But if the world, its Honour and Glory be coveted after by you, as the Nation feareth it is too much, then will the Lord ariſe <hi>for your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,</hi> and as a Whirl-wind from the moſt higheſt <hi>Shall it ſuddenly come upon you;</hi> and as a mighty Tempeſt, great and terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble againſt the wall, and as a ſweeping Rain that leaveth no food; and his Lambs will he ſave, and his People and Heritage he will himſelf deliver: &amp; your portion ſhall be as in the book of the Pſalms. It is written <hi>Acts</hi> 1.20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.25. <hi>Let his habitation be deſolate, and let no man dwell therein, and his Biſhoprick let another take.</hi> Now this was <hi>Judas</hi> the Traitor, that was both <hi>a Biſhop,</hi> and <hi>Minister,</hi> for the work is one. For he was numbred with the Apoſtles (mark, <hi>Judas</hi> numbred, and choſen by Chriſt, and took part of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry with the Apoſtles) a thing that ye never came to as yet; but he cared not for the ſoul, the poor were diſpiſed by him; but like <hi>Balaam,</hi> and many now adayes, that are falſly called Miniſters of Chriſt, he loved the reward of Iniquity, and with that he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed a field, which is called <hi>the field of blood</hi> to this day. And fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down headlong, he burſt aſunder in the middeſt, and his bowels guſhed out: Let this be the reward of the wicked from the Lord, and the Recompence of the Perſecutor from the God of my Salvation; but the Righteous, let him be ſaved by the Lord, with an everlaſting Salvation from my God, becauſe he is poor and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, and abhorred of men, and hath no deliverer in the earth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:64060:4"/>
               <hi>O Watchman of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>O Shepherd of the Sheep, that have follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee, and for thy Names ſake have been willing to lay down their own lives, that in thee, and thy life, they may be found blameleſs, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ſpotleſs. O! Do thou ariſe thou great Shepherd of the everlaſting Covenant, ſave thy-people, preſerve thy Lambs, and in thy Armes carry them that are young; preſerve the feeble, and ſuch as be of a contrite Heart and Spirit, that none may touch thy hidden and anointed ones, ſo as to harm them in their inward parts, or wound them in their hidden life. O! Be thou abiding place unto them in the Storm, and a Light in their Tabernacles, when darkneſs covers their Enemies; that ſo in their Spirits, thy Sons may ſing together, and the morning Stars make Mellodie unto thee in their hearts; and the inhabitants of</hi> Sion <hi>ſhout for joy, that the Lord is in the midſt of them. Do this for thy heritage, and forſake them not Eternall God; we have heard with our ears, O Lord, the triumphing of the wicked is ſhort, O let it not be ſaid by them for ever,</hi> Where is now their God: <hi>But Ariſe, ariſe as in the dayes of old, and worke wonders for thy ſeeds ſake as in the antient time, when thou didſt march through the Sea with thy choſen, and didſt get thee a Name of praiſe from the foundation of</hi> Iſrael: <hi>So let it be with thy Enemies O Lord as of old, when the Stars in their courſe fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst</hi> Siſera.</p>
            <p>O Friends! I am a Lover of your Souls; and the eye is open, and opening daily in thouſands, and a numerous number begin to ſee the ſad ſtate they have been long in: O the Lord hath done a wonder, and a marvellous work he hath wrought in this our day which is dawned, the Day-Star is riſen in the hearts of thouſands, and the day that is everlaſting is dawned, and in <hi>England</hi> the ſun is riſen that ſhall never ſet again; &amp; the light thereof ſhineth, &amp; ſhall ſhine more and more, untill the perfect day; which the Clouds of the evening, nor the ſhaddow of the Mountains ſhall never cover again: the Lyon is rouzed, the Beaſts of the field ſhall tremble; the Lord is working, and who ſhall hinder, or let him?</p>
            <p>The Light is the eye, which ſeeth this day, which was open in <hi>Abraham,</hi> and in his Head who is inviſible and eternall, who ſaith, <hi>Before Abraham was, I am.</hi> This eye muſt be opened, and looked with, in you Biſhops; and the eye that doth offend and perſecute the precious Life, phickt out, and caſt away, and the hand cut off, and the Right Arm of the wicked broken before the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Arm, which is under-neath, in which the Shepherd of <hi>Iſrael</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:64060:4"/>doth carry his Lambs, can be known or wrought with by you.</p>
            <p>I ſay, till this eye be opened, and a new tongue be unlooſed, ye are but <hi>blind Watch-men</hi> and <hi>Leaders</hi> of the blind into the <hi>Ditch</hi> and <hi>horrible Pit;</hi> and <hi>Dumb Shepherds,</hi> that gather not the Sheep and out-caſt of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but ſuch as the Prophet ſpeakes of, <hi>That fed themſelves with the fat and cloath with the fineſt of the wool, and bewrayed him that wandereth; ye gather not the out-caſt; but with force and cruelty ſcatter the flock, which his own blood hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The eye being blinded, that ſhould put a difference between the Precious and the Vile, the Sheep and the Goates, the Diſeaſed and the Whole, the Strong, and the Weak: This is a great work. O Friends! to watch for the ſoul: The world by wiſdom, nor the learned by outward learning, know not the ſoul of man, nor what it is that the Anguiſh and pain is upon: but he that made it knoweth the frame thereof, and he that breathed into it the breath of Life, his eye, which is the Light, ſeeth and knoweth it altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: ſuch knowledge is too wonderful for me, that when this eye is awakened, I am ſatisfied therewith: O bleſſed is that eye that ſeeth and is ſatisfied therewith. O this is the eye that runs to and fro thorough the whole earth, and ſeeth the ſecret thoughts of all your hearts, in your bed-chambers; &amp; your Councel againſt the Lords people, is not hid from it in the darkeſt night that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>came;</hi> he ſeeth our innocency, and knoweth how we are wronged, by being numbred with tranſgreſſors. Is this the way to convert us to God, as <hi>Whipping, Perſecuting</hi> and <hi>Impriſoning,</hi> to the ſpoiling both of our bodies &amp; goods? Well, this is the way they took with Chriſt our Lord and Maſter; I ſay, thus was it in the Green tree, and with the Maſter of the Family, and generall Aſſembly, but not to convert us (were we unconverted) but we are on the earth, though not of it; and our bodies in priſon, though our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are at liberty; and he that was dead, now liveth, and is aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of the reach of all Perſecutors.</p>
            <p>I ſay, <hi>after he was</hi> (who is) <hi>aſcended, and all power in heaven and earth given unto him, and he had received gifts for men, having led Captivity that which did Captivate, and he having ſpoiled Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and Powers, by the power and virtue of his Reſurrection; he being aſcended, which firſt deſcended into the lowest parts of the earth; he that was in the the pit, death, hell and the grave, being made a little lower than
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64060:5"/>the Angels.</hi> I ſay, when he was glorified with the ſame glory he had with the Father, before the world of iniquity began; then <hi>he gave ſome Apoſtles, Biſhops and Teachers:</hi> (Mark) not Lord Biſhops over the faith of Gods heritage; but <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints, and edifying the body of Chriſt, untill they all came into the unity of the faith and knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man in Chriſt:</hi> (Mark) <hi>untill he be</hi> formed, unto the meaſure and Stature of the fulneſs of Chriſt, that they ſhould be no more Children, toſſed and carried about with every wind of doctrine, to turn again into ſuch beggarly Rudements, as <hi>the obſerving of dayes, new Moones or Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths,</hi> or <hi>abſtaining from meats:</hi> the forbidding of which, the Apoſtle calls <hi>a Doctrine of Devills,</hi> which God hath created and commanded to be eaten, and nothing to be refuſed by them that are come to Chriſt and in him believe, who is the Body and End of all Shadows; and the Word that Sanctifies the Meats, who is the Everlaſting day, in which the Children of the Light do walk, as it is written, and witneſſed in theſe latter dayes (of the man of ſin) The Children of the Lord, ſhall be taught of the Lord; in whoſe Light the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of them that are ſaved ſhall walk; and great ſhall be the Peace, and Aſſurance of his children in that day; it ſhall be unto them a good day, and a Joyful day, a day of Feaſting, and Glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heart; a Good day, and a Holy day, a day of Praiſe, and Thanksgiving, wherein the wicked ſhall ceaſe from Troubling, and where the weary ſhall be at Reſt: there the Priſoners reſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and hear not the voyce of the oppreſſor.</p>
            <p>Conſider ye that are Commanding <hi>to abſtain from Meats,</hi> which God hath commanded to be eaten, and commanding to <hi>Swear,</hi> and <hi>Obſerves dayes,</hi> which God hath forbiden, ſaying, <hi>Six dayes ſhalt thou labour, and do all thy work:</hi> O will ye limit the Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that are in the Truth, and ſuch who ſtand in the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made them free?</p>
            <p>Will ye Judge them <hi>in Meats,</hi> and condemn about <hi>Holy dayes</hi> of your own making? (as ye call them) are ye wiſer than God? or muſt the Precepts of men be obſerved, rather than the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of God, who ſaith, by his Spirit (that muſt not be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited) <hi>All things are lawful to be eaten by them that know the Truth?</hi> O what is your end, that God muſt not be hearkened unto? is not filthy luker your end? that can for mony ſell a Diſpenſation, to do that which your Law condemneth as unlawful; and what muſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64060:5"/>the poor do that are ſick, and have ſcarce mony <hi>to buy meat,</hi> much leſs <hi>to buy a licence</hi> to eat it; let all theſe Laws <hi>be diſanul'd,</hi> and thoſe Statutes that are contrary to the Statutes of God, <hi>be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by you no longer,</hi> upon any pretence whatſoever.</p>
            <p>And for theſe things that are Righteous and Good, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we cannot break Chriſts Commands, (no other thing can be juſtly charged againſt us) how are we drawn from our families, <hi>Husbands</hi> from <hi>their Wices,</hi> and <hi>Wives</hi> from <hi>their Children,</hi> (<hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> never ſaw the like) leaving them deſolate without any helper in the earth? as Sheep for the Slaughter, ſo are we killed all the day long, and counted as the off-Scowring of all things for Righteou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſneſs Sake, becauſe we follow him, <hi>Who is the Lord our Righteouſneſs,</hi> &amp; obey his Righteous Commands, rather than the Unrighteous Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and Commandements of men; therefore are we Perſecuted, and Hated by them that know not our Innocency, and judged not meet to live upon the earth: And to hide themſelves, <hi>The Cry,</hi> is, (as in all ages the Perſecutors have done againſt the Lords People and Heritage) <hi>They are Enemies to the King,</hi> or <hi>no Friends to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government</hi> or elſe, as the cry is now againſt the diſpiſed Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, <hi>Deceivers, Deceivers,</hi> &amp; ſuch <hi>As deſtroy all good Laws and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> this was done in the green tree; and this was done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Apoſtles in Generations paſt; and in this preſent age the cry is, <hi>Theſe are the falſe Chriſts,</hi> and <hi>falſe Prophets that Chriſt ſaid ſhould come, Mat.</hi> 24. v. 5, 24.</p>
            <p>Now let all people conſider the Scripture in the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>John,</hi> chap. the 2. ver. 18, 19, 26. chap. 4. ver. 1, 2, 3, 5. Read theſe Scriptures, and you ſhall find Chriſts Words were fulfilled ſixteen hundred years ago, and that the Quakers are not the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; But ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> complaines of with weeping, Phil. 3.18. <hi>They were ſuch who were Enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt, whoſe God was their Belly,</hi> and <hi>minded earthly things;</hi> and ſuch as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpake of, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Epiſtle, chap. 2. or like Demus, <hi>who forſook Chriſt</hi> and the true Apoſtles, <hi>and imbraced the preſent world, becauſe the love of the Father was not in them.</hi> And if I ſay like the Miniſters in England, <hi>Which ſeek their Gaine from every quarter,</hi> I lie not.</p>
            <p>But conſider what Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Ye ſhall know them by their fruits.</hi> Read <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> before mentioned, v. 1. <hi>But there were alſo falſe Prophets among the people, even as there ſhall be falſe Teachers among you, who ſhall privily bring in damnable Hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and many ſhall follow there
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64060:6"/>pernicious Wayes; by Reaſon of which, the way of truth ſhall be evill ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, and through covetouſneſs,</hi> (Mark, is not this a Proverb in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who is more Proud and Covetous than our Miniſters?) <hi>Shall they with fained words make merchandiſe of you,</hi> v. 10. <hi>Theſe are they that walk after the fleſh in the luſt, which have the fained words, who were Deſpiſers of Government,</hi> v. 15. <hi>Which have forſaken the Right Way, whoſe hearts are exerciſed with covetous practiſes, curſed Children, being gone aſtray in the way of</hi> Balaam, <hi>the Son of</hi> Bozer, <hi>who loved the wages of unrighteouſneſs: theſe are Wells without water, Clouds that are carried with a tempeſt, to whom the miſt of darkneſs is reſerved for ever.</hi> Read <hi>Johns</hi> Epiſtle which ſaw that fulfilled before his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, which Chriſt foretold in <hi>Matthew</hi> ſhould come, Joh. 4.1, 2. <hi>Beloved, believe not every Spirit, but try the Spirits,</hi> (Mark) what muſt they try the Spirits with? <hi>With the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction</hi> and <hi>Annointing which was in them,</hi> Were they to try the Spirits whether they were of God, chap. 2.18. <hi>Little Children, it is the laſt time, and as ye have heard that Antichriſt ſhall come, even now are there many Antichriſts, whereby we know that it is the laſt times: they went out from us,</hi> (Mark) as I ſaid before, from the true Apoſtles who were in the light, and had fellowſhip with the Father and the Son, v. 20. <hi>But ye have an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction from the Holy One, and ye know all things,</hi> v. 24. <hi>Let that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore abide in you,</hi> (mark, in you) <hi>which ye have heard from the beginning, if that ſhall remain in you, ye ſhall continue in the Son and in the Father.</hi> v. 26. <hi>Theſe things have I written to you, concerning them that ſeduce you</hi> v. 27. <hi>But the annointing which ye have received of him abideth in you,</hi> (mark in you) <hi>and ye need not that any man teach you, but as the ſame annointing teacheth you of all things, and is truth, and is no lye; And even as it hath taught you, ye ſhall abide in it. And now little Children, abide in him; for ye know he that doth Righteouſneſs, is born of him,</hi> ch. 4.3. <hi>This is that Spirit of Antichriſt, whereof ye have heard that it ſhould come, and even NOW already is come into the world: little children, ye have overcome them, becauſe, greater is he that is in you, than he that is in the world; they are of the world, therefore ſpeak they of the world, and the world heareth them, as you may read,</hi> Rev. 13.3, 8. <hi>and all the world wondered after the beaſt, and worſhiped the Dragon (who was wrath with the Woman, and made war with the Remnant of her ſeed, which kept the Commandement of God, and have the teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt)</hi> they worſhiped the Dragon which gave power to the Beaſt, and they worſhiped the Beaſt; ſaying, <hi>Who is like unto the beaſt? Who is able to make war with him?</hi> Rev. 17. and 3, 8. <hi>Let him that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64060:6"/>readeth underſtand.</hi> v. 1. <hi>Come hither, and I will ſhew thee the Judgement of the great Whore that ſitteth upon many waters:</hi> (mark) <hi>waters are Multitudes, Nations, Tongues and Peoples; and the Woman which thou ſawest, the Mother of Harlots, is Miſtery Babilon, which Reigneth over the Kings of the earth, with whom they commit fornication, and drink of her Cup of fornication,</hi> ver. 3. alſo the ver. 2. <hi>So he carryed me away into the wilderneſs in the Spirit: And I ſaw a woman ſit upon a ſcarlet coloured beaſt, full of Names of Blaſphemy, and the Woman was arraied in Purple, and Scarlet colour, and decked with Gold, and pretious Stones and Pearles:</hi> (Mark, the out-ſide was very beautiful, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable by the world, whoſe Names are not written in the Lambs Book of Life before the foundation thereof) but this Woman, the falſe Church, had in her hand <hi>a cup full of Abomination and filthyneſs, of which the Nations drank,</hi> &amp; were made <hi>drunk,</hi> &amp; unſtable <hi>as waters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let him that readeth, know the miſterie of the Beaſt, [and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand who is that falſe Prophet and Antichriſt,] which carried the woman. Read chap. 13.6. <hi>Is not this he that openeth his mouth in blaſphemy againſt God, to blaſpheme his Name and Tabernacle, and them that dwell in heaven?</hi> This is that Antichriſt which oppoſed Chriſt. v. 7. <hi>And it was given unto him to make war with the Saints, and to overcome them, and Power was given him, over all Kindreds, Tongues and Nations.</hi> v. 15. <hi>And he had power to give life to the image of the Beaſt that it ſhould ſpake.</hi> [mark] This is that compelling power which would cauſe all to worſhip the Image, inſtead of the life: and the likeneſs inſtead of the true God; <hi>And he cauſeth all, both Rich and Poor, Small and Great, Bond and Free, to receive the mark in their Right Hand, or in their Fore-Heads, and that none might buy or ſell, that would not worſhip the Image of the Beaſt, but ſhould be killed.</hi> Here is the patience of the Saints. Here are they which keep the Commandements of God, and the Faith of Jeſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And I ſaw the Woman Drunk with the Blood of Saints,</hi> [Mark, this is not the Woman that fled from the face of the Dragon, which brought forth the Man-Child,] <hi>And with the blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus: and when I ſaw her, I wondered with great admiration; but the Angel ſaid, wherefore didſt thou marvell?</hi> [Mark, <hi>John</hi> was wondring alſo, till the Angel ſpake to him, ſaying,] <hi>I will tell thee the mistery of the Woman, and of the Beaſt that carryed her: the Beaſt that thou ſaweſt was, and is not, and ſhall aſcend out of the bottomleſs pit, and go into per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, &amp; they that dwell on the earth ſhall wonder, whoſe Names were not written in the book of Life from the foundation of the world, when they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64060:7"/>behold the beaſt that was, and is not, and yet is: theſe ſayings are faithfull and true, teſtified by his Spirit, who is the faithfull and true witneſs, That the everlaſting Goſpel ſhall be preached again unto every Nation, Tongue and People; and</hi> Babylon <hi>the Great, the Mother of Harlots, ſhall come in Rememberance with the Lord, and her fleſh ſhall be burned with fire and the Beaſt and falſe Prophet which have deceived the Nations, ſhall be taken and east alive into a lake of fire burning with brimstone; and the Merchants of the earth ſhall mourn, and ſuch as trade by Sea, and are made rich with her Merchandiſe, ſhall</hi> weep <hi>bitterly,</hi> and <hi>ſhall ſay,</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, alas, <hi>That great City, that great City that was cloathed in fine linen,</hi> [Mark, this fine linen is not the Righteouſneſs of the Saints, but the paint of the Harlot gone from God] <hi>Purple and Scarlet, and decked with Gold, and precious Stones and Pearls, for in one hour ſo great Riches is come to nought: and every Ship-Maſter,</hi> [Mark, ye Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who are unſtable] <hi>And all the Companies in Ships, and Sailers, and as many as trade by Sea stood afar off, and oryed when they ſaw the ſmoak of her burning,</hi> ſaying, <hi>What City is like to this great City! And amighty Angel took up a Stone like a great Milstone, and caſt it into the Sea,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Thus with violence ſhall this great City</hi> Babylon <hi>be thrown, and ſhall be found no more at all, and the light of the Candle ſhall ſhine no more in her</hi> [for it ſhall be put out] <hi>And the voyce of the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom, and of the Bride ſhall be heard no more at all in thee; for thy Merchants were the great Men of the Earth,</hi> [Mark, the great Men of the Earth traded with her, and drank her Cup] <hi>in whom was found the blood of Prophets and of Saints. And of all that were ſlain upon the Earth for by her ſorceries were all Nations Deceived; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rejoyce euer her, thou Heavens, and be glad of heart, you Saints for evermore; Rejoyce you holy Apoſtles, and Prophets, for God hath avenged your blood on her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, all you great men in <hi>England,</hi> be wiſe; Ye Judges, and you Councellers, receive Inſtructions from the Lord; <hi>Counſel</hi> is better than <hi>Stength,</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom</hi> better than <hi>Weapons of War;</hi> but your Strength, nor the Strength of your King, is not to impriſon the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and children of the Promiſe, and Heirs of the Kingdom, and World that hath no end; ſhould you not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtand up, and make Reconciliation between the Lord and his people, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, and lift up the priſoner out of the pit; and gather all into the Light (Chriſt) to whom the gathering of the people ſhall be.</p>
            <p>Now if you ſay, <hi>We perſecute you not, you keep not the Kings
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64060:7"/>Law;</hi> my anſwer is, if <hi>Haman</hi> were clear of the Jewes deſtruction, (<hi>Eſther</hi> 3) ever the more, becauſe of the Kings Decree, and a Law made againſt them; then are you clear of our ſufferings alſo: Why would you make us beleive <hi>the Word of a King</hi> is nothing worth, who hath promiſed, <hi>We ſhould live in the liberty of a good Conſcience in his Dominions, ſo long as we lived peaceably,</hi> which hitherto we have, and ever ſhall do? for herein do we exerciſe our ſelves dayly, to have a Conſcience void of offence, both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and man: And if you harm us for that which is good, Chriſts light in your conſcience will condemn you; but was not KING CHARLES miſ-informed, as King <hi>Ahaſhuerus</hi> was, by <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> that Courtier, who told the King, <hi>the people of God were not fit to live in his Dominions?</hi> and are not we as greatly wronged by ſome of you, as the Jewes were by <hi>Haman?</hi> ver 8. <hi>There is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine people,</hi> ſaid Haman, <hi>Scattered and Diſperſed among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in all the Provinces of thy Kingdom; and their Lawes</hi> (mark) [they did Woſhip another God] <hi>are divers from all people, neither keep they the Kings lawes,</hi> which was, <hi>that all ſhould bow to</hi> Haman; much like that law, <hi>That none ſhould meet together in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to Worſhip the Lord.</hi> And this is my caſe, who hath been a priſoner 18 weeks, nothing laid to my charge, but the keeping on my <hi>Hat</hi> to <hi>Richard Brown,</hi> Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> [ſo called] whether ſuch thing ought to be ſuffered by the King, and his Councel, the Lord be Judge; Therefore, conſider ye Judges, is this the way of the Judge of all the Earth? or the way to Eſtabliſh the Kings Throne? nay, the Lord ſees it, and will plead our innocencie, who hath ſaid, <hi>The Kings Throne is Eſtabliſhed in Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or could the Courtiers, pertaining to King <hi>Darius,</hi> be clear of <hi>Daniells</hi> being caſt into the Lyons Den, then you may be clear of ſo many thouſands of us, being caſt into Priſons, and Dens, as it is at this day. Read <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Then theſe Preſidents, and Princes, ſaid, We ſhall not find any occaſion againſt this</hi> Daniel, <hi>except we find it againſt him, concerning the Law of his God. Then they came and told the King, The Governours and Princes, the Councellers and the Captaines have conſulted together to Eſtabliſh a Royal Statute, and to make a firm De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, That whoſoever ſhall as any Petition of any God or Man, ſave of thee, O King, for thirty dayes, he ſhall be caſt into the Den of Lyons. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore King</hi> Darius <hi>Sealed the Writing, and the Decree:</hi> Now <hi>Daniel</hi> did not forbear worſhiping his God, as we do not forbear meeting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64060:8"/>becauſe of the Kings Decree, therefore came his Enemies and accuſed <hi>Daniel,</hi> as our enemies accuſe us; that we are diſ-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garders of the King, and his Law: Now, little did <hi>Darius</hi> know what deſigne theſe men did purſue, that their envy was rather againſt <hi>Daniel,</hi> then to honour the King; though they did pretend it was for his honour, that they made ſuch a Royall Decree, as they called it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But when the King heard theſe things, how was he diſpleaſed with himſelf, and ſet his heart on</hi> Daniel <hi>to deliver him; and he laboured tell the going down of the Sun, to deliver him, but could not.</hi> Now let all Flatterers be warned, and Proud men take heed how they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe KING CHARLES againſt the Lords people, or endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to deſtroy them whom the Lord hath bleſſed; and let them know they are but men; and <hi>our God,</hi> whom we ſerve, and worſhip, notwithſtanding the Kings Command to the contrary, <hi>is the living and true God,</hi> and his Arm is not ſhortned, but he is the ſame as ever he was in the dayes of <hi>Mordecay,</hi> Eſther 3. or in the dayes of <hi>Daniel,</hi> Daniel 6.22. And therefore, the Sons of <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhall not be conſumed, though they may ſuffer perſecution many dayes, yet ſhall they not be forſaken: but out of all Tribulation ſhall the Lord deliver them, and ſave them from the hand of the violent man.</p>
            <p>And now to your conſideration, by whom we ſuffer, (whether as evil doers, or well doers, the Lord is Judge, and knoweth right<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>well) I propound theſe few Queſtions in the fear of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Whether to obſerve Dayes, and Times, were not the ſin of</hi> Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>who filled Jeruſalem with Innocent blood? and whether to Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſpoile our bodyes and goods, for opening our ſhops, and working on the ſix dayes, be not contrary to the Command of God?</hi> which ſaith expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Six dayes ſhalt thou labour, and do all thy work: and contrary to the Apoſtles Doctrine, which ſaith,</hi> I fear I have beſtowed on you labour in vain, while ye obſerve Dayes, New-Moons, and Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, <hi>Which were but a Shaddow of good things to come, but the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was Chriſt?</hi> Colloſſians 2.17, 18.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Whether it be not in your hearts, who are laying ſuch a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for Perſecution, to fill</hi> London, <hi>and the</hi> Nation <hi>with Innocent blood, as</hi> Manaſſes <hi>did</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>if ſuffered by the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Whether Chriſt be the Light, that hath enlightened eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, or the Grace that hath appeared unto every man, and able to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64060:8"/>ſave to the uttermoſt, able to Guide, Teach and Lead into all Truth, all that receive, and believe in it?</hi> If yea, <hi>Then whether all</hi> Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds, Doctors, Biſhops, and Teachers <hi>whatſoever, that make it not there work to turn peoples minds to the light within, be not falſe Shepherds,</hi> and <hi>ſuch as</hi> Jeremy, <hi>Eſay, Ezekiel,</hi> and <hi>Mied,</hi> cryed againſt, who ſaid, <hi>He was given for a Covenant of light, for a teacher and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his people, that he might be Salvation to the ends of the earth?</hi> Iſa. 2.6, 7. Iſa. 49.6, 9. Who alſo propheſied, <hi>That the Nations which were ſaved, ſhould walke in the light of the Lord, and the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſhould come to his light, and Kings to the brightneſs of his Riſing?</hi> Iſa. 60.3. Iſa. 2.5.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>And whether all ſuch</hi> Biſhops <hi>do not deny their work, and ſeek themſelves, and worry the flock of Christ, That ſet up any worſhip, (though they get a Law made by the powers of the Nation to establiſh it) if it be not in Spirit and truth only, and according to</hi> Pauls <hi>Doctrine and Work, which was</hi> to turn people from the darkneſs to the light, from the power of Satan unto God, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. That remiſſion of ſins might be received, and an inheritance amongſt them that are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified in the light, in the Faith. <hi>Whether it be not a vain worſhip, being neither according to the Scriptures, nor you led thereunto by the Spirit of the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, <hi>Whether all Worſhip, that is taken up from the letter of the Scripture,</hi> [Nothing differing to the outward act,] <hi>from the Saints of old, as ſinging</hi> Davids <hi>Pſalmes, Preaching and Praying, and the like, whether all this be not a vain worſhip, and to the Lord Abomination? Yea, or Nay.</hi> I ſay, <hi>If not led thereto by the Eternall Spirit of the Lord?</hi> Seeing God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in Spirit and Truth, as it is written, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, <hi>Whether they are like to do the work of an Evangelist, or perfect the Saints, or bring into the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Faith, or to any meaſure of Chriſt, who are not in the Light, nor led by the Spirit, as it giveth utterance to them that Preach, ſeeing the Scripture ſaith, the true Worſhip</hi> is in Spirit, and <hi>the true Miniſters</hi> ſpake as it gave them utterance? Acts 2.4. <hi>But are Perſecuting and Impriſoning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout dayes, the Children of the Light, who walk in the ſubſtance, the Everla ting day, who ſaith,</hi> Swear not at all, <hi>who is the Lord of the Sabboth, and the Word of the Oath, which was ſince and before the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:64060:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Seventhly, <hi>Whether this may not be for a</hi> Lamentation <hi>in</hi> England, <hi>that ſo many thouſand of the Lords people,</hi> (called Quakers) <hi>who have lived peaceably, ſince they were a people, ſhould now be impriſoned, their bodies and goods ſpoyled in Dungrons, Holes, and Priſons, ſo ſoon after the</hi> Word of a King to the contrary, <hi>becauſe we cannot forſake Chriſt in not meeting together, and break his Command, who is the Shepherd of his Sheep, and Biſhop of the Souls, and ſaith,</hi> Swear not at all? <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.33, 38. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.12</p>
            <p>Now let all that ſear the Lord, be Judge, whether this be diſobedience to Magiſtrates, to be obedient to the Lord; and whether God be not rather to be obeyed than man, or any Commands or Lawes which are contra y to Scripture? And whether the Law was added to a Righteous man, or becauſe of the unrighteous and lawleſs? whether they that a e in Chriſt, and walk in, and ſpake the Truth, and do righteouſly, and as they would be done unto; whether they do not fultil the Righteouſneſs of the Law? and what Law that is, will harm them in this condition.</p>
            <p>And now, O ye Biſhops, Doctors, and Teachers, and Rulers of the people, my love is to your immortal ſouls, and iſſueth out towards you, becauſe of the Ruler of the people, whoſe love is in my heart: go not on to perſecute an Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent people; cauſe them not to ſuffer, that never had any hand in your Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which you, &amp; your King, are lately come out of: ſince we were a people, we did never Plot, or do Violence to any Government, (but the government of Satan in the heart) and our Weapons were never Carnal ſince we had a being, but Spiritual, to the pulling down of ſpiritual wickedneſs; but in the Lord we have, and do honour all men, and ſubmit to all their Righteous Commands, <hi>Who Rule for God, and are a Terror to evil doers, and Praiſe to them that do well;</hi> to them <hi>are our ſouls Subject, and to their Commands, for the Lords ſake;</hi> but as for theſe Commands, which are contrary to Scripture, and the Spirit of the Lord in our hearts, by Suffering, ſhall we rather chuſe to bear our Teſtimony againſt, though commanded by a King, or Parliament; and if we ſuffer by them, it is for Righteouſneſs ſake; and not as Theives, Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, or as evil doers; but as Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>And the living Lord is our <hi>Shepherd,</hi> and <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and with him have we peace, and good will towards men, ſuch as our Perſecuters cannot take from us; elſe we ſhould have ſainted before this day, had not we beleived in the Lord, who leads us, and inſtruſts as by his holy ſpirit in the path we ſhould go. And waters, and keeps us as the apple of his own eye, in patience under our bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, that we ſaint not in all our Tribulations; and this is my love, though I ſuffer for it: I leave it to the Lord, and his Eternal Councel, to you, do not lay a foundation for Perſecution, though it be too much laid already, yet go not on; think not <hi>Sion</hi> will be built with blood, or Jeruſalem upon the Ruin of the people, whom the Lord hath bleſſed, and choſen for his peculiar Treaſure; for they are the bleſſed of the Lord, that made Heaven and Earth; and they that touch them will he rebuke for their ſakes, as he rebuked Kings in the dayes of old, ſaying, <hi>Touch not my anointed, and do my Prophets no harm,</hi> 1 Chron. 16.17, 22.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
